<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles ministred by the reuerend father in God. Anthony by the grace of God Bishop of Chichester to the churchwardens throughout the whole diocesse of Chichester, at the visitation begun there the 6 of September 1600, and to bee enquired of quarterly within the saide diocesse</title>
            <title>Visitation articles. 1600</title>
            <author>Church of England. Diocese of Chichester. Bishop (1596-1605 : Watson)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00170</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10180</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111833</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847098</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847098</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12109</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00170)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12109)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 222:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles ministred by the reuerend father in God. Anthony by the grace of God Bishop of Chichester to the churchwardens throughout the whole diocesse of Chichester, at the visitation begun there the 6 of September 1600, and to bee enquired of quarterly within the saide diocesse</title>
                  <title>Visitation articles. 1600</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Diocese of Chichester. Bishop (1596-1605 : Watson)</author>
                  <author>Watson, Anthony, d. 1605.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By T. East] for Thomas Charde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>In the copy catalogued the date of publication altered in MS. to read 1604.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12109:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12109:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ARTICLES MINI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred by the Reuerend <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in God Anthony by the grace <hi>of God Biſhop of Chicheſter to the</hi>
               </hi> Churchwardens throughout the <hi>whole Dioceſſe of Chicheſter, at the</hi> viſitation begun there the 6 of <hi>September</hi> 1600, <hi>and to</hi> bee enquired of quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly within the ſaide Dioceſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London for Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Charde.</hi> 1600.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles_of_visitation">
            <pb facs="tcp:12109:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12109:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Articles to bee enquired of within the <hi>Dioceſſe of Chicheſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="part"><!-- @N removed: "common prayer" -->
               <head>Touching the place of Common Praier in the Church.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether the Chauncell, Church and Chappell bée ſufficiently repaired as well in ſtone, Timber, Leade, Tyle, Glaſſe, as all other neceſſary things, &amp; if they bée not, through whoſe default this is omitted.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whether your Churchyarde bée ſufficiently fenced and decently kept, &amp; the trées therein growing not ſpoiled.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Whether the walles of the Church bée within whited, &amp; beautified with fruitfull ſentences out of the holy Scriptures: and paued comely in the bodie of the Church &amp; the Chancell.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Whether you haue in your pariſh Church &amp; Chappell, all thinges neceſſarie for the ſetting forth of common praier and adminiſtration of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> namely the booke of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon praier, two Pſalters in proſe and méeter: the Engliſh Bible in the largeſt volume, which now is authoriſed by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Biſhops of this Realme: the two tomes of Home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies: the Paraphraſes of Eraſmus in Engliſh: the table of the ten Commandements of God: a conuenient Pulpit well placed, a decent table ſtanding on a frame, for the holy <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,</hi> with a faire linnen cloth to lay vpon the ſame, and ſome couering of ſilke, buccharam, or other ſuch like, for the kéeping cleane thereof, a comely <hi>Communion</hi> Cup of ſiluer, with a couer of ſiluer for the ſame, which may ſerue for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the <hi>Communion</hi> Bread: a decent Surplus with large ſléeues: a Regeſter booke in parchment of Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, weddings, &amp; burials: a ſure cofer with thrée lockes &amp; keies for the kéeping of the ſaid regiſter booke.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Whether all monuments of ſuperſticion bée defaced and cleane remoued: as Alters, Roodeloftes, Copes, Veſtments,
<pb facs="tcp:12109:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> Holy water, Stockes, Images, and all popiſh bookes either Latine or Engliſh.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Whether you haue a Clarke, Sexten, or decon, to aſiſt your prieſt dutifully in reading the pſalmes, firſt leſſon, the Epiſtle, and ſuch other ſeruices: &amp; alſo to kéepe the bookes and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Church, the Church it ſelfe, the quier, the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> table, the Pulpit &amp; the Font, faire cleane and decent, againſt the time of ſeruice of the Communion, Sermon and Baptiſme, and by whom he is choſen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part"><!-- @N removed: "church service" -->
               <head>Touching ſeruice vſed in the Church.</head>
               <p n="7">7 Whether there bée any within your pariſh, or elſe where néere about the ſame, and within this Dioceſſe, to your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or as you haue heard, that commeth not to Church, but is a recuſant in that point: or that commeth, but vſeth not to ſtay during the time of deuine ſeruice and Sermons, or doth not receiue the Communion in his pariſh Church, thrée times yéerely at the leaſt.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Whether doe you know or haue heard any within your pariſh, or néere about the ſame, within this dioceſſe, to heare or ſay Maſſe, or any other ſeruice not publiquely allowed, or to receiue, entertaine, or lodge any prieſts, ſeminaries, Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites, or other deprauers or miſtikers of the Eccleſiaſticall ſtate or gouernment, and what bée their names.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Whether you doe know or haue heard of any, within your pariſh or néere about the ſame, within this Dioceſſe that vſeth to diſwade any perſon from the Religion now profeſſed, or to perſwade any to the Romiſh religion.</p>
               <p n="10">10 Whether doth your Parſon, Vicar, or Curat, or the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Vicar, or Curat, or any other of any other pariſh within this Dioceſſe, néere vnto you, to your knowledge, or as you haue heard, vpon ſundaies and holidaies, vſe to ſay morning and Euening Praier, and the Letanie diſtinctly, and in ſuch manner &amp; forme, and vnder ſuch words as are ſet forth and preſcribed in and by the booke of Common Praier: if no, then what other forme or manner, hath he or doth he or they vſe, &amp; what hath he or they omitted or added in any of the premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, other then is in the ſaide booke expreſſed.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12109:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>11 Whether doth your Parſon, Vicar or Curat, or the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Vicar, or Curat, or any other of any other pariſh, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Dioceſſe, and néere about you, to your knowledge or as you haue heard, vſe the miniſtration of the Lords Supper and Baptiſme, the inſtruction of children, ſolemnization of Matrimonie, the viſitation of the ſicke, the buriall of the dead, and the churching of women, in ſuch manner and forme, and vnder ſuch words, rites and ceremonies, as are ſet forth and preſcribed in &amp; by the ſaid booke of Common praier: if no, then what other forme doth hée or they vſe, and what hath hée or they vſed to adde or omit of, in or about the premiſes, or any of them: &amp; doth he or they vſe to omit the Ring in Marriage, and croſſing the Childs head in Baptiſme.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Whether hath your Parſon, Vicar or Curat, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther within your pariſh, or elſe where néere about the ſame, &amp; within this Dioceſſe, to your knowledge, or as you haue heard, preached, declared, vttered, or found fault with, or ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken any thing againſt the ſaid booke of Common praier, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing in the ſaid booke expreſſed, or againſt any doctrine, office, function, or calling Eccleſiaſticall, within this Realme by publique authoritie eſtabliſhed: or againſt the ordinance &amp; election of Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Prieſts, Decons, or any of them, and what was the ſame thing or fault ſo found, vttered declared, or preached, and by whom.</p>
               <p n="13">13 Whether hath your Parſon, Vicar, or Curat, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther within your pariſh or elſe where, néere about the ſame, and within this Dioceſſe, to your knowledge or as you haue heard, preached, declared, vttered, ſpoken, or ſignified in writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, word or déede, any thing in liking, maintayning, extolling, commending, or perſwading, of any other doctrine, diſcipline or any other forme of Common praier, election or ordination of any other offices, officers Decons, Paſtors, Elders, preſbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries or Eccleſiaſticall Cenſures, then are by the lawes and ſtatutes of this Realme eſtabliſhed.</p>
               <p n="14">14 Whether you haue on Wedneſdaies and Frydaies ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice in your church and chappell, according to order appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for all our neceſſities ſet forth by authoritie.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12109:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>15 Whether your Parſon, Vicar, or Curat, doe euery ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day when ther is no ſermon, read plainely ſome part of the Homelies preſcribed to be read: or whether any of them not being found to haue ſufficient abilitie to preach, or not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully admitted therevnto, doe take vpon them to expound any part of the ſcripture &amp; therby omit the reading of the homelies.</p>
               <p n="16">16 Whether the Communion bée adminiſtred euery mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, where there be forty houſeholds in the pariſh otherwiſe once euery quarter at the leaſt at the diſcretion of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
               <p n="17">17 Whether your Miniſter, or any other within the pariſh or elſe where in this Dioceſſe, to your knowledge or as you haue heard, hath publiſhed, ſpread abroad, deliuered, ſolde, or vttered, or receiued, retained, or kept any Engliſh bookes ſet forth by an Engliſh papiſt beyond the ſeas, either againſt the Quéenes Maieſties ſupremacie in matters Eccleſiaſticall: or againſt true Religion and Catholike doctrine, now receyued or ſet forth by any other within this Realme or elſe where, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſtate of the Archbiſhops, Biſhops, and Clergie of this Realme: or againſt the doctrine, orders &amp; ceremonies now retained by publique authoritie.</p>
               <p n="18">18 Whether your Parſon, Vicar, or Curat, doe preach or cauſe to bée preached, euery moneth one Sermon at the leaſt, and whether there-in they doe foure times in the yéere, teach the people that all forraine vſurped authorytie is iuſtly aboliſhed: and that the Quéenes Maieſtie is and ought to bée the ſupreame gouernour ouer all perſons, &amp; in all cauſes, as well Eccleſiaſticall as ciuile, within hir dominions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part"><!-- @N removed: "baptism" -->
               <head>Baptiſme.</head>
               <p n="19">19 Whether your Children that bée in no great perill of death, bée baptiſed after the laſt leſſon of Morning prayer at the Font, vpon the ſunday or holy day next after the birth thereof, with Godfathers and Godmothers that can ſay the Catechiſme, the Lords Prayer, the Articles of the Chriſtian faith, &amp; the ten Commandements, and whether your Miniſter hath refuſed to baptiſe any child at any day in the wéeke, in caſe of great weakeneſſe.</p>
               <p n="20">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12109:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>20 Whether any child borne within your pariſh, hath not béene baptiſed in your pariſh Church.</p>
               <p n="21">21 Whether your children baptiſed at home in caſes of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame weakeneſſe and infirmitie, bée brought to the Church after their recouery, that the Miniſter may examine whether they be lawfully Baptiſed or no.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part"><!-- @N removed: "marriage" -->
               <head>Matrimonie.</head>
               <p n="22">22 Whether they haue married any maner of perſons with out the banes aſking thrée ſeuerall ſundaies or holy daies in time of deuine ſeruice, in the preſence of the people.</p>
               <p n="23">23 Whether they haue ſolemnized any marriage in the night ſeaſon, or at vnlawfull time of the day.</p>
               <p n="24">24 Whether they haue married any of diuers pariſhes with out a certificat of the banes aſking, from the Miniſter or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, where the parties dwell, or elſe doe ſolemnize any marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age out of their owne Church, or marrie any in their owne Church, which be not of their owne pariſh.</p>
               <p n="25">25 Whether your Miniſter or Curat exhorteth yong perſons not to make any contract of marriage priuatly or openly, with out the conſent of their parents &amp; friends that haue authoritie ouer them, according to Gods law and mans law.</p>
               <p n="26">26 Whether they marry any that cannot ſay perfectly the Lords praier, the articles of a Chriſtian mans faith, and the ten commandements of God.</p>
               <p n="27">27 Whether any man haue two wiues, or any woman two huſbands.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part"><!-- @N removed: "visiting sick" -->
               <head>Viſiting the ſicke.</head>
               <p n="28">28 Whether they haue béene dilligent according to theyr duety, in viſiting and adminſtring vnto the ſicke, to call the loſt ſhéepe to Chriſtes fold by repentance, comforting them with godly and wholeſome ſentences out of the ſacred ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture &amp; Gods word, whereby they may put their whole truſt in the mercies of God in Chriſtes death our Sauiour, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning the world, and in forgiuing all men as they would be forgiuen at Gods hand.</p>
               <p n="29">29 Whether they haue exhorted all perſons, aſwell in health as in ſickneſſe, to make their Teſtaments, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb facs="tcp:12109:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> their goods, for the diſcharging of their conſciences, the quietnes of their wiues and children, &amp; ſatiſfieng of the world.</p>
               <p n="30">30 Whether they doe exhort their pariſhioners to cauſe a bell to be tolled for them &amp; their families in the time of their ſickneſſe, to the intent they may be commended vnto Gods mercy by the praiers of other men.</p>
               <p n="31">31 Whether they haue called vppon them that haue made their teſtaments, to beſtow according to their abilitie ſome part of their goods vpon the true workes of mercy: as vpon the poore and néedie, vpon the fatherleſſe and motherles, vpon deſolate widowes and marriages of poore maidens, vpon the maintenance of the miniſtrie &amp; Schooles, vpon the reparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Church, high waies and ſuch like, and whether the Churchwardens call for the ſame.</p>
               <p n="32">32 Whether they haue béene diligent to bury the dead being brought to the Churchyard, vſing no other ceremony then is appointed for burialls.</p>
               <p n="33">33 Whether after the deceaſe of any perſon there is any more ringing then one ſhort peale before the buriall, and an other after the buriall.</p>
               <p n="34">34 Whether there bée any exceſſiue ringing or toling vſed vpon ſundaies or hollidayes, or their euens, ſauing to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer, and to a Sermon, or ſuch as doe not tend to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſticion, and to the maintenance of popiſh purgatorie and of praier for the dead.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part"><!-- @N removed: "commination" -->
               <head>Commination.</head>
               <p n="35">35 Whether they vſe out of the pulpit in a publique aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly to read the commination againſt ſinners once euery quarter, immediatly after the Letanie is ſaid vpon ſome ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day or holliday.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part"><!-- @N removed: "ministers' function" -->
               <head>Touching the Function of Miniſters.</head>
               <p n="36">36 Whether your Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, doe trauaile diligently &amp; painefully, according to their abilitie to ſet foorth true religion, to adorne the ſame with the examples of good life, to beate downe, vice, ſuperſticion, Idolatry, papiſtrie, &amp; all manner of hereſies: to exhort all men to vnity, peace, and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly loue, &amp; to their dutifull obedience to their Prince &amp; ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:12109:5"/> as hée in authoritie vnder hir, vnto the diligent hearing, reading, and teaching of Gods word.</p>
               <p n="37">37. Whether they indeauour to haue the pariſhioners to ſay ſeruice and ſing Pſalmes in proſe and méeter with them in the Church.</p>
               <p n="38">38. Whether they ſay the common prayers, reade their Pſalmes and Chapters, and other prayers, ſo audibly plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and diſtinctly, in conuenient time, and at ſuch a place, as all the people may well heare, and vnderſtand the ſence ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to their edifying.</p>
               <p n="39">39. Whether they vſe after morning and euening prayer ſayd, to beſtow themſelues in godly meditation of good lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and inſtructing of youth.</p>
               <p n="40">40. Whether they vſe the exhortation ſet foorth in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Lords Supper, thereby to ſtir vp theyr pariſhioners to the oftner receiuing of the ſame.</p>
               <p n="41">41. Whether they haue admitted any notorious offendour or malicious perſon, or any notoriouſly knowen to bée out of charitie, or that hath done any open wrong to his neighbour eyther by word or by déede, to the holy Communion, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out open acknowledging of their fault and reconciliation.</p>
               <p n="42">42. Whether there be any in your pariſh, that readeth any priuate Lectures in the ſame, or vſeth expoſition of ſcriptures in any priuate mans houſe whatſoeuer, or that preacheth any Doctrine of innouation, to with-draw the people from theyr due obedience: and whether any Preacheth, and doth not at certaine times in the yéere, miniſter the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſay ſeruice according to order. Alſo whether any new preſbiterie or conſiſtorie of Elders bée in the pariſh ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, or any priuate Conuenticle of thoſe whoſe eares ich with ſingularities, and impertinent matters, in the which ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall Miniſters bée admitted to deale in the Eccleſiaſticall function and ſuch as deſpiſe rulers &amp; ſpeake euill of them that are in authoritie, or whether any of your pariſh contribute to ſuch ſchiſmaticall dealings and conuenticles.</p>
               <p n="43">43. Whether doth your miniſter or any other, vſe any ſolemne Feaſtes or publique exerciſe, vpon any day not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted
<pb facs="tcp:12109:6"/> by publique authoritie: and who were at the ſayde feaſt or exerciſe.</p>
               <p n="44">44. Item, whether doth your Parſon, Vicar, or Curat or any other, preach, expound, interpret, exerciſe or Catechiſe, in any priuat méetings or conuenticles within your pariſh wher are the ſame held, and who reſort thereto.</p>
               <p n="45">45. Whether doth your Parſon, Vicar, &amp; Curate, at their Sermons, Lectures, or exerciſes, pronounce all that forme of prayer for hir Maieſtie and the whole Realme, ſet foorth in the end of the Quéenes Iniunctions.</p>
               <p n="46">46. Whether doth your Miniſter bid all ſuch holydayes and faſting dayes, as are appointed by the booke of common prayer, and ſay ſeruice vpon the ſame holidayes, and vpon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Wedneſday and Friday: and doth any of your pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners worke vpon any of the ſayd holidayes.</p>
               <p n="47">47. Whether your Parſon, Vicar, or Curat, doe Preach, expound the Scriptures in his owne cure, or in any other place, not being lycenced ſo to doe by the Ordinarie.</p>
               <p n="48">48. Whether any Curat or Miniſter bée ſuffered to ſerue in the Church, before hée bée examined and admitted by the ordinary in writing vnder the ſeale of his office, and before he ſhew his lycence vnto the Churchwardens.</p>
               <p n="49">49. Whether the Regiſter of all weddings, burialls, and chriſtnings within your pariſh, be well kept, and a coppie of them once euery yéere, within one moneth after <hi>Eaſter,</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the regiſter, and whether the Quéenes Maieſties Iniunctions be quarterly read.</p>
               <p n="50">50. Whether yéerely in the Rogation wéeke, for the better knowing and retayning of the circuite of your pariſh, &amp; for the obtayning of gods bleſſing vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruits of the ground, the Parſon, Vicar, or Curat, the Churchwardens and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine other of the ſubſtantiall of the pariſh, with other of the younger ſort, walk the accuſtomed bounds of the pariſh, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or ſinging in Engliſh the hundred and third, the hundred and fourth pſalmes, the Letanie with an homily deuiſed for that purpoſe, and other deuout prayers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part"><!-- @N removed: "ministers' behaviour" -->
               <head>Beehauiour of Miniſters.</head>
               <p n="51">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12109:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>51. Whether your Parſon or Vicar be reſident vpon his benefice, and kéepe hoſpitalitie according to his abilitie.</p>
               <p n="52">52. Whether they kéepe their manſion houſes and chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels in good ſufficient reparations.</p>
               <p n="53">53. Whether they kéepe in their houſes any perſons, men or women ſuſpected of euill life, or of euill religion.</p>
               <p n="54">54. Whether your Miniſter or Curat be ſuſpected of any notorious crime, as of filthie lucre, couetouſneſſe, adulterie, blaſphemie, periurie, drunkenneſſe, idleneſſe, filthie and vaine talke, or elſe is flaunderous in any part of his conuerſation, thorow brawling, fighting, quarrell picking, &amp; peace breaking.</p>
               <p n="55">55. Whether they haunt ale-houſes, tauerns, Innes, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuſpected place, or vſe any vnlawfull gaming, as daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, carding, dicing, hawking and hunting.</p>
               <p n="56">56. Whether your Miniſter and Curate doe vſe at home and abroad ſuch apparell as publick order appoynteth to bée decent for them to weare, and that their wiues, children and families, bée appareled handſomly without vanity, and great charges fit for the calling of their huſbands, and doe vſe the Surples at the time of common prayer.</p>
               <p n="57">57. Whether your Parſon or Vicar hath at any time ſince the thirtéenth yéere of the Quéenes Maieſties raigne, made any manner of leaſe or graunt of his Parſonage or Vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridge, or any part thereof, he being abſent and not riſident vpon the ſame, to any other then to his Curat that dyd or doth ſerue his cure in his abſence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part"><!-- @N removed: "schools" -->
               <head>Schooles.</head>
               <p n="58">58. Whether the Schoolemaiſters &amp; Teachers within your pariſh, be examined, allowed or licenſed by the Ordinarie vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his ſeale, whether they teach the Grammer ſet foorth by King <hi>Henry</hi> the eyght, and no other: whether they teach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing contrarie or repugnant to the order, Doctrine, and ceremonies of this church of England by publique authoritie eſtabliſhed, and whether they teach the Catechiſme in Latin, ſet foorth <hi>Anno.</hi> 1570. and allowed, and ſuch other Godly learning, as may induce them to godlineſſe, true religion and good conuerſation.</p>
               <p n="59">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12109:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>59 Whether they doe encourage the youth committed to their charge, to the loue of true religion, and godlines, cauſing them daily, comming and departing from the ſchole, to pray vnto God for increaſe of learning &amp; godly life, and alſo teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them ſuch ſentences of the holy ſcriptures, as may frame them to feare God &amp; liue vertuouſly, and alſo cauſing them to ſay grace in Engliſh before meat &amp; after, and to giue thanks to God for all his benefites that they at any time receiue of his mercy, and not of their deſerts.</p>
               <p n="60">60 Whether your Scholemaiſters be negligent in teaching, or elſe be common officers, farmers, artificers, or otherwiſe intangled in other affaires, that they cannot benefit their ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers in learning, and what ſchoolemaiſters be in any priuate houſe.</p>
               <p n="61">61 Whether aſwell the Schoolemaiſter as the ſcholers doe come to ſchoole and leaue it in due time and houres.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part"><!-- @N removed: "hospitals" -->
               <head>Hoſpitalls.</head>
               <p n="62">62 Whether your Hoſpitals, ſpittles, and Almes houſes, be well repaired and godly vſed, according to the foundation &amp; auncient ordinaunces of the ſame, and whether there bée any other placed in them, then poore impotent and néedy perſons, that haue not wherewith or whereby to liue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part"><!-- @N removed: "churchwardens" -->
               <head>Churchwardens.</head>
               <p n="63">63 Whether your Churchwardens be choſen yéerely one by the pariſh or the maior part thereof, and the other by the Miniſter, vpon the day accuſtomed.</p>
               <p n="64">64 Whether at any time héeretofore, the Churchwardens, or the Miniſter, or the pariſhioners, or any of them to your knowledge, or as you haue heard, haue with-held or detained in their cuſtody, or haue ſold, waſted, ſpent, or otherwiſe alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated any of the Church goods or ſtocke.</p>
               <p n="65">65 Whether the Churchwardens yéerely in writing, make their accounts to the pariſh, as well of all receipts as of their neceſſary expences.</p>
               <p n="66">66 Whether they doe leuy for not comming to the Church to heare deuine ſeruice vpon ſundaies &amp; holidaies, xii. pence, for euery perſon abſent without lawfull cauſe, or preſent euery
<pb facs="tcp:12109:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſuch perſon.</p>
               <p n="67">67 Whether they doe waſt or ſpoile any part of the church goods &amp; whether they call for all manner of legaces giuen to the poore of the pariſh, to the reparations of the Church, and ſuch other good vſes, &amp; whether they call for the mony due to be paid for thoſe that are buried in the Church.</p>
               <p n="68">68 Whether the Miniſter of the Church &amp; the Churchwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, doe certifie in writing vnder their hands and ſeales to the Ordinary at leaſt wiſe 14. daies before the Aſſiſes or quarter Seſſions, throughout all the whole yéere, all ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as be abſent from hearing diuine and publique ſeruice in the Church, the ſpace of a moneth together at any time, that the ſame certificat may be deliuered to the Iuſtices, and the offenders therin indited according to a ſtatute, what lands tenements, anuities, or goods or chattels are belonging to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vſe about the Church and in whoſe hands the euidences thereof remaine.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part"><!-- @N removed: "midwives" -->
               <head>Midwiues</head>
               <p n="69">69 Whether your Midwiues be honeſt, ſober, and ſkilfull, void of ſuperſticion, drunkenneſſe, &amp; vnſéemely behauiour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part"><!-- @N removed: "parishioners" -->
               <head>Of the Pariſhioners.</head>
               <p n="70">70 Whether the Pariſhioners and euery of them doe come dayly vpon the ſundaies and holydaies to church, or kept o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen his ſhop, or done any worke vpon any ſuch day, or vſed at any time to braule or fight in the Church or Churchyarde, or vſe Maygames, Lords of Miſrule, dauncing, on the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baoth day, or holy day in time of deuine ſeruice.</p>
               <p n="71">71 Whether any that kéepeth an Alehouſe, Tauerne, or Inne or any other, ſuffereth any to daunce or play at any vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full game, or vttereth any meate or drincke, in time of diuine ſeruice, either of Sunday or holiday.</p>
               <p n="72">72 Whether there be any within your pariſh, or néere about you within this Dioceſſe, ſuſpected or knowne to tell fortunes, to help men to things loſt, vſe charmes, witchcraft, ſorceries, ſoothſayings, prophecieng, or any ſuch other ſuperſticious and deuilliſh illuſion: whether any within your pariſh haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted adultery, fornication, or inceſt, or be a common drunc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>karde,
<pb facs="tcp:12109:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> or a common ſwearer, or an vnlawfull vſurer, aboue ten in the hundreth, or is ſuſpected of any of the premiſſes.</p>
               <p n="73">73. Whether any within your pariſh do entertaine or kéepe in his houſe, or other place, any woman ſuſpected to bée of lewde life, or any woman with childe, and after hir deliuerie ſhall ſuffer hir to depart, before ſhe haue done pennaunce, and how many ſuch haue you knowen or heard of.</p>
               <p n="74">74. Whether the people vpon any occaſion do eate or drink in the church, or any excommunicate perſon hath intruded himſelfe into the church at the time of common prayer, and who doth kéepe company with any excommunicate perſon, knowing him ſo to bée.</p>
               <p n="75">75. Whether euery houſeholder, their wiues, children and ſeruaunts, doe vſe to make prayers vnto God euery mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, before they goe to their worke, and euery euening bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they goe to bed.</p>
               <p n="76">76. Whether they, their Children and ſeruaunts, béehaue themſelues reuerently in time of common prayer, preaching, or miniſtring of the Sacraments, without walking, talking, ſléeping, or diſturbing the congregation.</p>
               <p n="77">77. Whether euery Pariſhioner haue framed himſelfe to receiue oft the holy Communion, and hath receiued at leaſt thriſe the Communion this yéere, according to the dutie of a Chriſtian man, and namely at Eaſter laſt, or receiuing haue not ſignified the ſame to the Miniſter, or haue not come to the Miniſter to be examined and to be better inſtructed touching his duety towards God and man.</p>
               <p n="78">78 Whether any man woman or child, vſe to occupie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe otherwiſe in the Church in the time of diuine ſeruice, then in praying and in marking attentiuely, that which is read or preached by the Miniſter.</p>
               <p n="79">79. Whether there bée any in the pariſh that preſume to execute or to miniſter the goods of thoſe that bée departed out of this world, without an adminiſtration or probate of teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or haue falſified, or ſuppreſſed the will of any perſon, or any executors that haue not fulfilled the teſtators will, &amp; hath not lawfully proued the ſame will before the Ordinarie.</p>
               <p n="80">
                  <pb facs="tcp:12109:8"/>80. Whether any childe being borne ſince the thirtéeneth yéere of the Quéenes Maieſties raigne, hath not béene brought to be baptized at his pariſh church.</p>
               <p n="81">81. Whether any miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iuer or doer, hath had his pennaunce or any part thereof omitted, without conſent of the Biſhop himſelfe firſt had.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part"><!-- @N removed: "patrons" -->
               <head>Patrons of Benefices.</head>
               <p n="82">82. Whether your Parſon or Vicar, or any other for him, hath for or in reſpect of any ſumme of money, reward, gift, profit or benefit directly or indirectly, or for or by reaſon of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny promiſe, agréement, graunt, bond, couenant, or other, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, of or for any ſumme of money, reward, gift, profit, or benefit what ſo euer, directly or indirectly, procured or obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the gift or preſentation of his benefice.</p>
               <p n="83">83. Whether you know any Patrone or any Aduouſoner in your pariſh, that hath made a gaine by any colour, deceit, or ſimoniacal pack, in beſtowing his benefice, or by receiuing money, or promiſe of the leaſe of the whole, or of part, or by reſeruing his owne tithes, or any penſion to himſelfe, his childe, ſeruant or friend.</p>
               <p n="84">84. Whether doth your Parſon or Vicar, let out, or ſuffer any to enioy his benefice, or any part thereof, or giue any penſion out of the ſame, or ſuffer any man to holde or enioy his owne tythes, or to enioy any of the gléebe land.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And you ſhall make and bring in your preſentments touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the Articles aboue mentioned, within four-teene dayes after the feaſt of Eaſter, Saint Iohn the Baptiſt, S. Michaell the Archangell, and the natiuitie of our Lord.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
